The truth is, at the moment,
social media is easier than it's ever been
before,
and you'll notice
that a lot of normal people
are blowing up.
I'm going to teach you exactly why,
and I'm going to give you all the lessons
as to
how you can do it yourself.
The content landscape has changed so much.
I've been creating content for 10 years.
I've got over a million followers on four
platforms, half a million YouTube
subs, 450,000 people on my email list.
And 10 years ago,
if you wanted to get seen
or you wanted to get eyeballs, I had to
write a blog and host it on WordPress.
Then I'd have to post that on Facebook
and hope people would read it.
I would then have to put a bloody HTML
link at the bottom to get people to join
my
email list.
I've been through 50 shades of content,
and these are the
changes that are about to happen.
The first thing that I'm making a point of
right
now is people are sick to death of
over-edited reels.
We definitely saw a turn through the
pandemic where people were all at home,
all on
their phones.
So because the competition became quite
fierce, everyone would
spend so much time editing B-roll, text,
overlay.
Everyone started saying you've got to use
hacks to get people to
follow your content,
and you've got to say things at certain
times.
Retention was the word that
was used so much.
To post a reel without any editing
was stupid. It was ridiculous.
What you had to do was exactly this
and exactly that.
But what happens is people get exhausted.
Now, if I use another example,
when we create advert creatives
and you spend
money trying to get impressions in front
of people, the ad or the platform, like
Meta, has to learn.
Then you go through a phase where the
advert does really well.
Then the advert exhausts.
And the reason it exhausts
is people have seen so
much of it that maybe they don't even
realize they're doing it, but they swipe
away. They scroll away.
You get a higher bounce rate.
But the same thing happens with styles
and modalities of content.
People were so sick of swish and SFX
and sound effects
and music and the dramatization.
It made them urge and
want more just a normal conversation with
someone.
Platforms like TikTok and Instagram
and Facebook all
striving to get you to watch reels
that were super, super highly
edited. People kind of had enough.
And the comeback that I spot at the moment
is something that I call the return of the
yap.
If you go on your news feed nowadays,
you'll see people just yapping away,
talking
about things, and you'll notice
that Instagram made it incredibly easy.
Actually, I'll pull over
and I'll show you now.
Instagram now,
if you want to create a reel,
you can just go into your phone.
You can just press a button,
and you can just talk to camera
and post it.
And you'll notice
that some of your favorite creators
are doing this, and they're
getting mad views because of it.
But the thing that they're doing
is quite smart.
It's quite clever. It seems off the cuff.
It seems like they've just got in their
car.
It seems like, "Oh, there's something
that I need to tell you about."
But yet the
structure of the reel is almost identical.
They've still got an incredible hook,
then they've got a setup,
then they've got a
payoff,
then they've got their call to action.
The structure of the reel never changed.
Just the format in
which they presented it did.
Another example of that is this right now.
I've got a studio.
I've got Sony FX3s.
I've got professional cameras
that film in 4K.
Yet,
I'm here recording on a DJI Pocket Osmo 3
in my car on
the way to the filming studio. Why?
Because sometimes people prefer a less
polished video.
I've been testing this on my YouTube
channel recently, this very channel that
you're watching.
And I do content critiques.
I go through people's stuff.
And by the way, if you want one of those,
there's a link in the description below.
And one video, on purpose,
I did the worst quality video ever.
No microphone, no camera.
I used the web camera on my computer
that's built into my monitor.
And the view is exactly the same.
Content is so much about what you say,
what you present, how you present it, not
necessarily how it looks
or how nice the camera is.
Now,
am I saying then never get a professional
camera?
Am I saying don't make your content look
nice? No.
What I'm saying is back in the day,
between 2018 and 2021, there was a bit
of a barrier to entry of getting into
content.
So
someone asked me to rev it, so I have to.
And there's a tunnel.
[car revving] Oh, there we go.
What I'm saying is
all you need is an iPhone,
or even this camera isn't expensive.
If you're willing to just talk to camera
to answer people's questions to help them
with their problems,
you can start to create a personal brand.
You don't even need to be
that well experienced in content creation.
You just need to start.
You just need to be willing to put out
dozens and actually
hundreds of pieces of content,
see what lands and what doesn't.
That's why so many normal people
are blowing up because before the
pandemic,
filming on your iPhone
and just talking to camera
when you're walking the dog
wasn't enough. But now it
is because people don't care anymore
if it's in 4K,
2K, 1080p. What they care about
is this person's
brand or what this person does going to
help me and my problems?
And if the answer to that is yes,
they're going to watch your content.
Now, there's another caveat on this.
Gary Vee's been talking a lot about how
follow culture is dead,
and I kind of agree
with him. Again Pre all of this,
you had to have someone follow you to
see your content. But now,
this channel has 50,000 subs,
but I have over
170,000 unique viewers watching my content
each month.
Now, some people could go, "Oh my God,
two out of three people don't follow you."
I
don't care. The thing
that I want to optimize for on the channel
the most is that
people watch the content. Outside of that,
I don't really care, and that's the way
you should be approaching it too. Yes,
I think followers is a good metric in some
respects, but only for the vanity
and the clout that it gives you.
The reality is, how many views
are your content getting?
How many comments
are you getting on each one?
So to summarize, people
are exhausted of over-edited content.
The yap is back,
but it doesn't just mean
that you chat crap to camera.
What it means is you can just pick up your
phone when you have an idea and
inclination.
Say you're a personal trainer
and a client's just asked you a
question. You go into the PT room
and you just say what it is
that you're thinking.
But just before you hit record, you think,
"What would be a good hook?" Everything
that you know about protein bars
is incorrect. Let me tell you why. Hook.
Now, what could you use for a setup?
Joe Wicks recently said
that ultra-processed foods
are killing you, and although I
agree with the sentiment,
he made a drastic mistake.
He went after protein bars.
Then you can have your payoff where you
could say whatever it is that you want,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Even though you've just filmed
that on iPhone, you
could get hundreds of thousands of views
on that.
Not highly edited,
not professionally filmed,
you're walking around, you're
just explaining to someone.
Because people now realize social media
isn't just a
contest of how nice your content is,
it's how well does it solve problems for
people. But the return of the yap
is in itself not going to help.
This is the way to structure your content
to make sure that you can really do this
in easy mode.
I call this the fist bump effect.
I want to make sure
that I put out so many pieces of content
on this channel, on
any channel, that should you see me,
you don't just think, "Oh, that guy's a
YouTuber." You feel compelled to come over
and say, "James, mate, your
content's changed my life,"
and you give me a fist bump.
Now, at this point,
if you've bought my stuff
or you've never bought my stuff, I
won't really care. Because
if the fact you've come over
and given me a fist bump,
that's enough. The fist bump effect
is not trying to get everyone in your
audience to buy your shit.
The fist bump effect
is getting everyone in your
audience to come over
and give you a fist bump.
Because if you can get a large cohort
percentage of your following to feel
inclined
to do that, a small percentage
are going to do business with you.
Now, as a business coach, if I
was to say to you 1% of your audience will
end up
doing business with you, ooh,
it's not a lot.
Trust me, 1% of your audience
is a hell of a lot, especially
if you grow and
nurture a decent size audience over time.
Those of you with 5,000 followers
and above, if you got 1% of people
working with you,
you'd have to hire someone else to help
you.
And the fist bump effect
is a great way to realize
that we're not trying to
optimize to be famous.
We're trying to optimize to get the fist
bump.
Because if someone has
that inclination to say hello,
to say thank you, to say, "I
owe you one," they're going to have the
same inclination to positively act
when you
ask them for a call to action. "Hey,
join my email list." "Hey,
do you mind signing
up to this?" "Hey,
I'm running a pre-sale." "Hey,
I'm running a wait list." I think
people are getting a bit nostalgic to how
the world was before AI.
You could see that trend recently,
the 2016 trend, where people
are looking back in
time going, "Oh, in 2016."
And I think people
are coming back to that.
Back before 2016, content
was conversational.
It was like a mate on the internet
was just giving you advice,
and then suddenly it
became all about trying to hack people's
attention to make your views look better.
Sorry, I'm at my gym.
The natural light was better before.
There we go.
[chuckles] Just to make you realize how
easy it is now.
Back in 2016,
I'd have to put one image
and text out a day.
I'd write one
blog on WordPress.
I can't even say the word because it's
been so ancient.
At the end of my blog, I would say,
"If you like that, you'll love my daily
emails." People would sign up to my emails
from that.
Then I didn't really know how to make
videos,
so I would just go live on my phone.
I would just hold my phone sideways
and just yap away,
and people would watch from
home,
and they would put it on in the evening
and just listen to me doing Q and As.
People would then join my email list.
I'd put out a marketing email every single
day.
And even before I had a business partner,
an app, in my first year of being online,
I was making about £4,000 a week, which
is crazy.
But now, I showed you
that Instagram feature.
There's another one on the new iPhone
where you can now record in
landscape mode on your iPhone holding it
portrait.
So as you're walking down the street,
you can now record YouTube videos
without--
Because if you hold it like this,
you're like, "Hello, my name is Jeff.
My name is Jeff."
But you can now hold your iPhone portrait
whilst recording
YouTube videos. That is massive.
But I could do a yap now.
Let me think of something. So Joe Wicks
is back in the news saying that, "I was
bought out by big food." I can then say,
"If you want to know more about this,
comment the word." Now, first of all,
that reel is going to get shown.
Thousands of people, many of which
that don't follow me,
they have the opportunity
to get interested, to follow,
to do whatever. Then the call to action.
We now have Mini Chat where we can put a
chat bot on.
Now, a lot of you
are complicating the Mini Chat feature.
You're trying to do an opening DM.
You're trying to get the email address.
To me, Mini Chat is best,
where your response just gives them a
link, and that link
just sends them to a squeeze page,
which is a page that you have with one
thing in
mind, which is to get their email address.
And then from there,
you have an email automation sequence
where you do it
proactively, whatever it is,
and then you warm them up
and convert them over time.
And then you're hitting them with those
emails.
But then at the same time,
because they're interested,
invested in your brand and
your content,
they're getting hit with your podcast,
your reels.
They're seeing your tweets
and your LinkedIn posts and blah, blah,
blah, blah,
blah, blah, blah, blah, bam,
they end up becoming a client.
So the best way to take advantage of this
is for a lot of you, you should bring the
editing down on your reels,
and then you should put the volume of the
amount of
content you're putting out up. Even
if it's a half the amount.
Like this video is just going to be simple
cuts.
So if the video's, I don't know,
20 minutes long, to preview the video,
it's going
to be 20 minutes plus add in the cuts.
I reckon I could edit this video in 22
minutes.
Then good packaging, boom, put it out.
So rather than spending a whole day doing
an edit, then day making three videos.
And I know what you're thinking,
"But James,
surely that's not what you preach."
Well,
the issue that a lot of people have
is they're trying to make perfect content
far too early on in their career as
if they've only got one shot,
but you don't.
There are things in life
that you do have one shot with.
For instance, who you have kids with.
And if you have kids with the wrong
person, that negatively affects your life
forever. But with content,
there's no penalties for making content.
So let's say we reduce the amount of
editing you're doing
and we put out way more
content. One of those videos
is going to do really, really well.
Then when that video does really,
really well,
then I would say let's go make it
again, but better.
Where we spend an hour on the
introduction.
Where we create props and setups
and stakes and analogies, and we buy
things on Amazon to make the point.
But for so many of you,
having less edited videos, more of them,
would be way
better for you at this stage in your
career.
You want to tell stories
and have a unique way of making your
point.
And my final point is this.
Most people give up way too soon.
In jujitsu,
I know it's really cheesy to say this,
but every black belt is quite
literally someone that got to blue belt,
didn't quit.
Got their purple belt, didn't quit.
Got their brown belt, didn't quit.
Think of this. There
are a lot of people
that have done jujitsu that aren't black
belts. The only reason as to why
that hasn't happened, catastrophic injury?
Not really. Very unlikely.
One of the best black belts in the world
doesn't even
have a developed hand.
He's only got a thumb and little finger.
João Machado,
probably just butchered his name.
He was born with a disfigured hand,
and he's still one of the best in the
world.
So you know if you've got a dodgy wrist
from rugby, that's not an excuse.
You just gave up.
And that's okay in some respects.
But in this game,
every single person you see online
that you admire,
respect, look up to, whatever,
they just got to a point where everyone
else thought
this isn't going to work,
and they just kept going. That's it.
You have to have a slight amount of
insanity to do this.
But I've made thousands of pieces of
content. Think about this.
My Instagram alone, four
and a half thousand reels.
YouTube, LinkedIn, Twitter.
Not to mention, I've probably written
4,000 or 5,000 email marketing emails.
Think of how little of that you've seen.
You see the car, you see my gym,
my filming studio, flying business class,
having a
multimillion-dollar drinks brand,
whatever, flex.
You see that,
but you just don't see tens of thousands
of pieces of content
that I did that bombed.
So why do you think you're so special
that you will get
everything you want in under 2,000 posts?
Why do you think
that you're so special
that you won't grow your email list to
where you want in under three years?
Why are you so special to think
that you can become a millionaire in under
five
years of hard work and grind?
The reality is the landscape is so easy
right now,
the only thing that's going to stop you
from being mega successful
is you.
The environment isn't going to make you
give up.
The economy's not going to make you give
up.
The only thing that's going to fuck this
up is you.
Getting rich and building a personal brand
today, the easiest it's ever been.
You don't have to believe me,
but I've got no incentive to lie.
I'm going to go lift some weights.
If you want to work with me, there
is a link in
the description.
I undercharge for the amount of time
and energy that I give.
And you don't just get access to me,
you get access to my people.
Declan, who's going to edit this video,
he's in the Discord.
Ollie,
who gave me the idea for this video,
he's in the Discord.
Cam, he's actually a student of mine
that was so good, I hired him full-time.
He's in the Discord. And me, I'm in the-
So if you fancy having your pants pulled
down or whatever, click that link
and I just challenge you to this.
Joining, I think, is like $3,000, $3,500.
How many new clients would you need to win
over to cover that cost?
Yeah, not that many. So join
or be a pussy and wait until it's twice
the price.
If not,
YouTube recommends this video here.
You watch that,
and eventually you stay in the ecosystem
of hearing me give advice
and you'll go, "Do you know what?
If he gives away this much for free,
imagine what
I'd get if I paid him." That's the thought
I want you to have.
Oh, here's your fist bump. See you inside.